Recently I visited Beloit, Wisconsin.
قمت مؤخرا بزيارة مدينة بلويت في ويسكونسن.
And I was there to honor a great 20th century explorer,
وقد كنت هناك لتكريم مستكشف عظيم من القرن العشرين،
Roy Chapman Andrews.
روي تشابمان أندروز.
During his time at the American Museum of Natural History,
خلال الفترة التي قضاها في المتحف الأمريكي للتاريخ الطبيعي،
Andrews led a range of expeditions to uncharted regions,
قاد أندروز مجموعة من الرحلات الإستكشافية إلى مناطق مجهولة،
like here in the Gobi Desert.
مثل هاهنا في صحراء غوبي.
He was quite a figure.
لقد كان علماً بارزاً.
He was later, it's said, the basis of the Indiana Jones character.
وقد كان في وقت لاحق، أساس شخصية إنديانا جونز.
And when I was in Beloit, Wisconsin,
وعندما كنت في بلويت في ويسكونسن،
I gave a public lecture to a group of middle school students.
ألقيت محاضرة عامة لمجموعة من تلاميذ المستوى الإبتدائي.
And I'm here to tell you,
وأنا هنا لأخبركم،
if there's anything more intimidating than talking here at TED,
أنه إن كان هناك شيء أكثر تخويفا من الحديث هنا في TED،
it'll be trying to hold the attention
فإنه سيكون محاولة الحفاظ على انتباه
of a group of a thousand 12-year-olds for a 45-minute lecture.
مجموعة مكونة من 1000 طفل في عمر الثانية عشر لمدة 45 دقيقة أثناء محاضرة.
Don't try that one.
لا تجربوا ذلك.
At the end of the lecture they asked a number of questions,
في نهاية المحاضرة طرحوا الكثير من الأسئلة،
but there was one that's really stuck with me since then.
ولكن كان هناك سؤال واحد علق بذهني منذ ذلك الحين.
There was a young girl who stood up,
كانت فتاة يافعة وقفت،
and she asked the question:
وطرحت السؤال:
"Where should we explore?"
"أين يجب أن نستكشف؟"
I think there's a sense that many of us have
أعتقد أن هناك شعورا يراود الكثير منا
that the great age of exploration on Earth is over,
وهو أن عصر الإكتشافات العظيمة على الأرض قد انتهى،
that for the next generation
وأنه بالنسبة للجيل القادم
they're going to have to go to outer space or the deepest oceans
سيكون عليهم الذهاب إلى الفضاء الخارجي أو إلى عمق المحيطات
in order to find something significant to explore.
حتى يجدوا شيئا ذا أهمية للاستكشاف.
But is that really the case?
ولكن هل هذا فعلا هو الحاصل؟
Is there really nowhere significant for us to explore
هل بالفعل لم يعد لدينا أي مكان ذي أهمية لاستكشافه
left here on Earth?
قد بقي هنا على الأرض؟
It sort of made me think back
جعلني ذلك نوعا ما أفكر رجوعا
to one of my favorite explorers in the history of biology.
في أحد المستكشفين المفضلين لدي في تاريخ البيولوجيا
This is an explorer of the unseen world, Martinus Beijerinck.
إنه مستكشف للعالم الخفي، مارتينوس بيجيرينك.
So Beijerinck set out to discover the cause
بيجيرينك قد انطلق لاستكشاف سبب
of tobacco mosaic disease.
مرض فسيفساء التبغ.
What he did is he took the infected juice from tobacco plants
وما فعله أنه أخذ العصارة الفاسدة من نبتة التبغ
and he would filter it through smaller and smaller filters.
ثم قام بترشيحها من خلال مرشحات أصغر فأصغر.
And he reached the point
ثم وصل إلى النقطة
where he felt that there must be something out there
حيث أحس بأنه يجب أن يكون هناك شيء ما
that was smaller than the smallest forms of life that were ever known --
أصغر من أصغر أشكال الحياة المعروفة على الإطلاق --
bacteria, at the time.
البكتيريا، في ذلك الوقت.
He came up with a name for his mystery agent.
ثم جاء باسم لهذا العامل الغامض.
He called it the virus --
فسماه الفيروس --
Latin for "poison."
والذي يعني "السم" باللاتينية.
And in uncovering viruses,
ومن خلال الكشف عن الفيروسات،
Beijerinck really opened this entirely new world for us.
فتح بيجيرينك حقا عالما جديدا بالكامل لنا.
We now know that viruses make up the majority
ونحن نعلم الآن أن الفيروسات تشكل غالبية
of the genetic information on our planet,
المعلومات الوراثية على كوكبنا،
more than the genetic information
أكثر من المعلومات الوراثية
of all other forms of life combined.
لجميع أشكال الحياة الأخرى مجتمعة.
And obviously there's been tremendous practical applications
ومن الواضح أنه قد كانت هناك تطبيقات عملية هائلة
associated with this world --
مرتبطة بهذا العالم --
things like the eradication of smallpox,
من قبيل القضاء على مرض الجدري،
the advent of a vaccine against cervical cancer,
ظهور لقاح ضد سرطان عنق الرحم،
which we now know is mostly caused by human papillomavirus.
والذي نعرف الآن أن ناتج غالبا عن فيروس الورم الحليمي.
And Beijerinck's discovery,
واكتشاف بيجيرينك،
this was not something that occurred 500 years ago.
وهذا لم يكن شيئا قد حدث قبل 500 سنة.
It was a little over 100 years ago
كان قبل ما يزيد قليلاً عن 100 سنة
that Beijerinck discovered viruses.
حين اكتشف بيجيرينك الفيروسات.
So basically we had automobiles,
وأساسا فإنه كانت لدينا سيارات،
but we were unaware of the forms of life
لكننا لم نكن واعيين بأشكال الحياة
that make up most of the genetic information on our planet.
التي تشكل معظم المعلومات الوراثية على كوكبنا.
We now have these amazing tools
والآن لدينا هذه الأدوات المذهلة
to allow us to explore the unseen world --
والتي تسمح لنا باستكشاف العالم الخفي --
things like deep sequencing,
أشياء مثل التسلسل العميق،
which allow us to do much more than just skim the surface
والتي تسمح لنا بأكثر بكثير من مجرد تصفح السطح
and look at individual genomes from a particular species,
وإلقاء نظرة على المورثات الفردية من نوع معين،
but to look at entire metagenomes,
بل النظر في مورثات فوقية بأكملها،
the communities of teeming microorganisms in, on and around us
المجتمعات المزدحمة للكائنات المجهرية فينا وفوقنا وحولنا
and to document all of the genetic information in these species.
وتوثيق كافة المعلومات الوراثية لهذه الأنواع.
We can apply these techniques
يمكننا تطبيق هذه التقنيات
to things from soil to skin and everything in between.
على التربة والجلد و على كل شيء بين الإثنين.
In my organization we now do this on a regular basis
ونحن نقوم بهذا في منظمتي على نحو منتظم
to identify the causes of outbreaks
لتحديد أسباب التفشيات
that are unclear exactly what causes them.
التي ليست معروفة المسبّبات بالضبط.
And just to give you a sense of how this works,
وفقط لإعطائكم فكرة عن كيفية عملها،
imagine that we took a nasal swab from every single one of you.
تخيلوا أننا أخذنا مسحة أنف من كل واحد منكم.
And this is something we commonly do
وهذا أمر نقوم به عادة
to look for respiratory viruses like influenza.
للبحث عن فيروسات الجهاز التنفسي مثل الإنفلونزا.
The first thing we would see
أول شيء سنراه
is a tremendous amount of genetic information.
هو الكمية الهائلة من المعلومات الوراثية.
And if we started looking into that genetic information,
وإذا بدأنا النظر في تلك المعلومات الوراثية،
we'd see a number of usual suspects out there --
سوف نرى عددا من المشتبه بهم المعتادين هناك --
of course, a lot of human genetic information,
وبطبيعة الحال، الكثير من المعلومات الوراثية البشرية،
but also bacterial and viral information,
لكن أيضا معلومات بكتيرية وفيروسية،
mostly from things that are completely harmless within your nose.
مصدر معظمها هي الأشياء الغير مؤذية تماما داخل أنوفكم.
But we'd also see something very, very surprising.
ولكن سوف نرى أيضا شيئا مفاجئة للغاية.
As we started to look at this information,
بعد بدأنا النظر في هذه المعلومات،
we would see that about 20 percent of the genetic information in your nose
رأينا أنه حوالي 20 في المئة من المعلومات الوراثية في أنوفكم
doesn't match anything that we've ever seen before --
لا تتطابق مع أي شيء قد رأيناه من قبل --
no plant, animal, fungus, virus or bacteria.
لا نباتات ولا حيوانات ولا فطريات ولا فيروسات ولا بكتيريا.
Basically we have no clue what this is.
وليست لدينا أي فكرة أساسا عن ماهيتها.
And for the small group of us who actually study this kind of data,
وبالنسبة لمجموعة الأفراد الصغيرة منا، والتي تدرس بالفعل هذا النوع من البيانات،
a few of us have actually begun to call this information
بدأ البعض منا بالفعل بتسمية هذه المعلومات
biological dark matter.
المادة المظلمة البيولوجية.
We know it's not anything that we've seen before;
ونحن نعلم أنه ليست مثل أي شيء قد رأيناه سابقا؛
it's sort of the equivalent of an uncharted continent
هي نوعا ما مكافئة لقارة مجهولة
right within our own genetic information.
تماما داخل معلوماتنا الوراثية الشخصية.
And there's a lot of it.
وهناك الكثير منها.
If you think 20 percent of genetic information in your nose is a lot
إذا كنت تعتقد أن 20 في المائة من المعلومات الوراثية في أنفك مقدار كبير
of biological dark matter,
من المادة المظلمة البيولوجية،
if we looked at your gut,
إن نظرنا في أمعائك،
up to 40 or 50 percent of that information is biological dark matter.
فإن ما يصل إلى 40 أو 50 في المائة من تلك المعلومات هي مادة مظلمة بيولوجية.
And even in the relatively sterile blood,
وحتى في الدم المعقم نسبيا،
around one to two percent of this information is dark matter --
ما بين واحد واثنين في المئة من هذه المعلومات هي مادة مظلمة --
can't be classified, can't be typed or matched with anything we've seen before.
لا يمكن تصنيفها، ولا يمكن كتابتها أو متطابقتها مع أي شيء قد رأيناه من قبل.
At first we thought that perhaps this was artifact.
في البداية كنا نظن أن الأمر ربما مصطنعة.
These deep sequencing tools are relatively new.
أدوات التسلسل التفصيلي هذه جديدة نسبيا.
But as they become more and more accurate,
ولكن عندما تصبح أكثر دقة فأكثر،
we've determined that this information is a form of life,
حسمنا في كون هذه المعلومات شكل من أشكال الحياة،
or at least some of it is a form of life.
أو على الأقل بعض منها شكل من أشكال الحياة.
And while the hypotheses for explaining the existence of biological dark matter
وبينما تظل فرضيات تفسير وجود المادة المظلمة البيولوجية
are really only in their infancy,
في مراحل طفولتها حقا،
there's a very, very exciting possibility that exists:
توجد هناك إمكانية مثيرة جداً:
that buried in this life, in this genetic information,
أنه مدفون في هذه الحياة، في هذه المعلومات الوراثية،
are signatures of as of yet unidentified life.
توقيعات لحياة غير معروفة بعد.
That as we explore these strings of A's, T's, C's and G's,
أنه ونحن نستكشف سلاسل الإي والتي والسي والجي هذه،
we may uncover a completely new class of life
قد نكشف الغطاء عن صنف جديد بالكامل من الحياة
that, like Beijerinck, will fundamentally change
والذي، ومثل بيجيرينك، سوف يغير جذريا
the way that we think about the nature of biology.
الطريقة التي نفكر بها حول طبيعة علم الأحياء.
That perhaps will allow us to identify the cause of a cancer that afflicts us
وربما سوف يسمح لنا بالتعرف على سبب السرطان الذي يصيبنا
or identify the source of an outbreak that we aren't familiar with
أو تحديد مصدر التفشيات التي لسنا على دراية بها
or perhaps create a new tool in molecular biology.
أو ربما إنشاء أداة جديدة في علم الأحياء الجزيئية.
I'm pleased to announce that,
ويسرني أن أعلن أنه،
along with colleagues at Stanford and Caltech and UCSF,
بالتنسيق مع زملاء في جامعة ستانفورد ومعهد كاليفورنيا للتكنولوجيا و UCSF،
we're currently starting an initiative
قد بدأنا حاليا مبادرة
to explore biological dark matter for the existence of new forms of life.
لاستكشاف المادة المظلمة البيولوجية بحثا عن أشكال جديدة من الحياة.
A little over a hundred years ago,
قبل ما يزيد قليلا عن مئة سنة،
people were unaware of viruses,
لم يكن الناس على وعي بالفيروسات،
the forms of life that make up most of the genetic information on our planet.
شكل الحياة الذي يشكل معظم المعلومات الوراثية على كوكبنا.
A hundred years from now, people may marvel
بعد مائة سنة من الآن، قد يتعجب الناس
that we were perhaps completely unaware of a new class of life
أنه قد كنا ربما غير مدركين تماما لصنف جديد من الحياة
that literally was right under our noses.
والذي كان حرفيا تماما تحت أنوفنا.
It's true, we may have charted all the continents on the planet
هذا صحيح، قد نكون قد رسمنا جميع القارات على كوكب الأرض
and we may have discovered all the mammals that are out there,
وقد نكون قد اكتشفنا جميع الثدييات الموجودة هناك،
but that doesn't mean that there's nothing left to explore on Earth.
ولكن هذا لا يعني أنه لا يوجد شيء باق لاستكشافه على الأرض.
Beijerinck and his kind
بيجيرينك وأمثاله من العلماء
provide an important lesson for the next generation of explorers --
يقدمون درسا هاما للجيل القادم من المستكشفين --
people like that young girl from Beloit, Wisconsin.
أشخاص مثل تلك الفتاة الشابة من بلويت، ويسكونسن.
And I think if we phrase that lesson, it's something like this:
وأنا أعتقد إذا صغنا ذلك الدرس، فسنحصل على شيء من هذا القبيل:
Don't assume that what we currently think is out there is the full story.
لا تفترضوا أن ما نعتقد أنه موجود حاليا هناك هو القصة الكاملة.
Go after the dark matter in whatever field you choose to explore.
اسعوا وراء المادة المظلمة في أي حقل تختارون استكشافه.
There are unknowns all around us
هناك مجهولات في كل مكان حولنا
and they're just waiting to be discovered.
هي فقط تنتظر أن يتم استكشافها.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)